so before we go into how exactly
tomasulo's algorithm Works let's kind of
see an overview picture of what's going
on in there just like what the hardware
structur looks like so first there is an
instruction Quee which I labeled here IQ
instructions come from the fetch unit in
the order in which they were fetched and
again these are only floating Point
instruction and then they're queued up
here so this is basically like this is
the kind of oldest instruction the next
one the next one the next one and we
will be kind of you know dropping these
instructions into the Tomaso's ALG
machine in the order in which they came
we always grab the next available
instruction from the instruction queue
and we want to put it into a reservation
station there are a number of
reservation stations that basically when
one becomes available we will put an
instruction into one of those and
reservation stations are where
instructions basically sit for their
parameters to become ready there is a
floating Point register file so this is
where your floating Point registers are
and when an instruction is inserted into
a reservation station the values that
are already in registers meaning the
values that are actually already present
and ready for execution are going to be
simply entered into the reservation
station from the register file once an
instruction is actually ready to execute
it goes to an execution unit and you can
have different types of execution units
so for example this is a adder and this
is a multiplier so simple floating Point
instructions would be done in the kind
of Adder unit and the more complicated
like multiply and divide would be done
in the multiplier unit
each of these units really had separate
reservation stations where instructions
that are going to that unit would wait
once such a unit has produced a result
the result would be broadcast on a bus
so of course the result would go to the
register file so prettyy much all the
results that are ready would be
available in the register file so that
instructions that come in would simply
grab them from there and we not don't
have to worry about where those values
are going to come from but these results
would also be broadcast to the
reservation stations why well because
the are instructions here that are
waiting for values that they need to be
produced and as values are produced we
need to tell these instructions that you
know now your value has been produced so
they need to also go here so pretty much
here you have some values that you
already have in an instruction some
values that you're waiting for and you
know what you're waiting for and then
when the value is finally broadcast you
check for each of the value that it's
broadcast whether this is the one we are
waiting for or not now I have two of
these per reservation station because a
typ instruction will actually have two
inputs like for example you're adding
two numbers and when you broadcast a
result either of the two or both of them
might need that result so for example if
you're doing something like add R1 R1
and the instruction that is producing R1
is currently in the multiplier when it
broadcast the result and says this is R1
we want to latch it into maybe both of
the operants for this instruction so you
need to compare basically what's being
broadcast its name needs to be compared
to both of the inputs that you are
waiting for and then you select the one
or both of them or none of them if this
is not the value you're waiting for and
finally if the instruction is not an
arithmetic instruction if it's actually
a load into the floating Point register
file or a store from it then the
instruction would go to the address
generation unit that's an integer
operation so it's not going going to go
through that so basically we just
compute the address and then we insert
the instruction into the load buffer or
a store buffer where the instructions
are going to be queued up for going to
memory and the load buffer only provides
a data address the store buffer provides
both the address and the data to memory
when a load comes back from memory its
value is also broadcast on the cdb and
goes to the appropriate register and
also all the values that are broadcast
from the bus are going to go here so
that stores can get their values when
they become available so a store
instruction that needs to put a value in
memory is going to wait for its floating
point value that needs to be placed to
memory
until it becomes available and only then
be sent to the memory unlike arithmetic
instructions which can execute out of
order basically they only wait for
inputs to become available and then they
can go for loads and stores they were
done in order so basically they didn't
reorder loads and stores and it will
later consider how to do that modern
processors will actually reorder loads
and stores too so this is a lot simpler
than in modern processors but this here
is pretty much the way it's done now
modulo some small adjustment
so before we go into kind of the details
of tomasulo algorithm let's just kind of
give names to some things on this
picture and then we will kind of discuss
what each of these things really needs
to do so this part here where we send
the instruction from the instruction
queue into the reservation stations and
the Lo store unit is called issue when
the instruction is finally sent to
execution from a reservation station is
called dispatch and when the
instruction is ready to broadcast its
result we call that right result or
simply broadcast so basically every
instruction will be issued meaning get
to the resing station eventually it gets
to dispatch because all of its inputs
are ready and uh it's kind of gets to go
to the unit once it's done it's going to
write the result and that is when we
consider the instruction completed so
now let's see what happens when you
issue when you dispatch and when you
write result